Guide to the Darlington Family Papers, 1753-1921 DAR.1925.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- William M. Darlington Papers, 1837-1889; III.
  - Collection Activities and Research, 1.
    William's Western Pennsylvania Historical Notes concerns legal events in Allegheny County, and include brief biographical notes on newly appointed judges. William also recorded information on proceedings and treaties brokered with the American Indians by early frontiersmen. Another section of this volume includes financial records concerning rent paid for several properties leased by the Darlington family. There are many loose pages within the journal and several pages are written entirely in French. For more information on this collection, please refer to Box 25, with oversized materials
    - William M. Darlington to A. Eaton, January, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Historical Society of Pennsylvania to William M. Darlington, July 1, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Certificate from State Historical Society of Wisconsin, September 12, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - J. M. Read, Jr., to William M. Darlington, September 5, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Charles Whittlesey to William M. Darlington, 1870-1872 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Statement by John Pennington, April 25, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Envelopes to William M. Darlington, ca. 1870-1885 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Isaac Samuel to William M. Darlington, February 8, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Letter to William M. Darlington from J. R. Lambdin, March 10, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - W.C. Reichel to William M. Darlington, July 8, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - William White to William M. Darlington, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Richard S. Edes to William M. Darlington, March 12, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Joseph Albree to William M. Darlington, March 31 1875 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - J. C. Hale to William M. Darlington, March 6, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Letter to William M. Darlington from John M. Newton, November 26, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - James Veech to William M. Darlington, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Letter from William M. Darlington to W. B. Hoff, May 1, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - J. L. Keyes to William M. Darlington, February 8, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Boyd Grumrine to William M. Darlington, May 30, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Sir to William M. Darlington, May 3, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Gilbert Cope to William M. Darlington, June 4, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - American History Magazine subscriptions and letter from Joseph Sabin, June 3, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Robert Clarke to William M. Darlington, December 2, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Receipts for Books purchased by William M. Darlington, August 21- December 11, 1885. (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - George P. Smith to William M. Darlington, April 15, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - George P. Smith to William M. Darlington, March 12, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - List of Hakluyt Society Publications, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Topographical Description, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - List of Books in William M. Darlington's Library at Guyasuta, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Catalog, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Inventory, Hall Bookcase, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - History Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Bouquet Papers Transcriptions, 1758-1763 (Box 2, Folder 6-13)
    - 18C primary source transcriptions, undated (Box 2, Folder 14-21)
    - Transcripts of Ettwein's diary, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Research notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 23-36)
    - Darlington Research Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Research notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-10)
    - Manuscript drafts, undated (Box 3, Folder 11-22)
    - Printed ephemera, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Classification of books in Darlington library at Guyasuta, undated (Box 1a, Volume 3)
    - Classification of books in Darlington library at Guyasuta, undated (Box 1a, Volume 4)
    - Classification of books in Darlington library at Guyasuta, undated (Box 1a, Volume 5)
    - Historical biographical notes, undated (Box 1a, Volume 6)
    - Book Orders, November 30, 1847- January 4, 1867 (Box 1a, Volume 7)
    - Research Notes, undated (Box 1a, Volume 8)
    - Financial Records, 1858-1859 (Box 1a, Volume 9)
    - Memoranda, ca. 1870s-1880s (Box 3, Volume 49)
    - The Improved Commonplace Book, ca. 1870s-1880s (Box 3, Volume 50)
  - Personal Papers, 2.
    This subseries contains personal letters from George P. Smith and Sergeant Winthropy, and a copy of a letter William wrote from Westchester, Pennsylvania, to an unknown correspondent who had requested information on cuttings and seedlings from Guyasuta. In 1862, William wrote to his brother, John, expressing happiness that John joined an Indiana regiment instead of a Pennsylvania regiment, as Indiana regiments were less likely to be sent to war. Also present are William's membership certificates from the Academy of Natural Sciences and the State Historical Society of Wisconsin, as well as a portrait of him at the time. For more information on this topic, please refer to Box 25, which contains oversized materials. The Record-Book included in this subseries appears to contain handwritten copies of Darlington's outgoing correspondence from 1838; it also includes accounts he documented from 1840 to 1844.
    - Sergeant Winthropy to William M. Darlington, August 24, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - William M. Darlington to Sir, October 22, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - William M. Darlington to John Darlington, February 7, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - James Brown to William M. Darlington, July 29, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - George P. Smith to William M. Darlington, November 20, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Norma Derry to William M. Darlington, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Unknown to William McCullough Darlington, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - George White to William M. Darlington, September 9, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - William M. Darlington Record-Book, 1838, 1840-1841, 1844 (Box 3, Volume 52)
  - Financial and Estate Papers, 3.
    This subseries contains documents relating to William M. Darlington's properties, investments, taxes and profession. Property records include a title to land in Allegheny County, an auction catalog of household goods inscribed to William, and a small notebook dated 1879 that lists bonds and mortgage payments. Additionally, two bound volumes, an account book and a book of financial records, document rent and mortgage payments, including payments from such institutions as the trustees of Jefferson College, and Snyder & Company. William owned stock in the Pittsburgh Manufacturing Company, the Sharpsburg Bridge Company, the Mercantile Library Hall Company, and paid taxes in Allegheny County and O'Hara Township. Also present are documents certifying William to practice law in Allegheny County and the state of Alabama.
    - Land surveys and abstract of title, 1803-1879 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Stock shares, January 13, 1812 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - State of Alabama to William M. Darlington, January 5, 1838 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Check written to cash, William M. Darlington, June, 1860 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Receipt for money paid by William M. Darlington to stockholders of Sharpsburg Bridge Co., September 25, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Auction Catalog, February 13, 1871 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Financial Notes, 1879 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Agreement, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Taxes, 1881, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Mercantile Library Hall Company Certificate for William Darlington, March 12, 1869 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Diaries, 4.
    William M. Darlington used these twenty-nine diaries to make brief notes about court dates, meetings, payments he received, the purchase of stocks, and other personal and professional transactions. The diaries occasionally mention William's health and personal habits. Many of the entries involve mortgage payments he received for various properties in and around Pittsburgh. Throughout the diaries, he describes the weather at Guyasuta, and occasionally notes the height of the Allegheny River. He also briefly mentions if he had received or sent any letters. In addition, William M. Darlington writes about legal cases in which he was engaged. Social events are occasionally mentioned, including parties at the homes of Mr. Lewis Hutchinson and Mr. McKnight in 1847 and 1848. Entries in 1873/4 and 1881/2 describe the Darlington family's travels in Europe. Three undated diaries contain historical research notes, including a list of officers that served at Fort Pitt, and information on various maps and books in the Guyasuta library. Corporate and personal names mentioned in the diaries include: Allegheny Company, Penn Railroad Company, Pleasant Valley Railroad Company, Monongahela Bridge Company, John B. Herron, J. H. Fibson, John Lundy, H. Fellman, Leo Schmidt, Reverend E. McKnight, E. P. Jones, and Dr. Harrison L. Robson.
    - Diaries, 1844, 1846-1847 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Diaries, 1847-1848, 1850 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Diaries, 1863-1864, 1869 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Diaries, 1870-1872 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Diaries, 1873-1874 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Diaries, 1875-1876, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Diaries, 1880-1882 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Diaries, 1883-1885 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Diaries, 1886-1887, 1889 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Diaries, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Mary Carson O'Hara Darlington Papers, 1753-1908; IV.
  Mary Carson O'Hara (1824-1915) enjoyed wealth and prominence inherited from her grandfather, James O'Hara, and from her Philadelphian grandmother, Mary Carson. Mary traced her O'Hara ancestry back to Tiege O'Hara, the last Lord of Leyney, Ireland. She studied at Edgeworth Seminary in Braddock's Field, now Braddock, Pennsylvania, and later in Staten Island at the renowned Mrs. McLeod's School. By the time she married William M. Darlington, she was a highly educated woman, well read not only in English, but Italian, German, French and Spanish. Mary and William had four children, three of whom survived into adulthood. The family resided at Guyasuta, an estate near contemporary Sharpsburg, Pennsylvania, that Mary had inherited from her father, Richard O'Hara. James O'Hara purchased the property from the United States government and named it after the famous Seneca leader, Guyasuta (c.1725–c.1794), from whom the Continental Army had purchased the land.
  Mary was passionate about regional history, and wrote Fort Pitt and Letters From the Frontier, and The History of Henry Bouquet and the Western Frontiers, 1747-1746, among other works. She also compiled a list of officers of the British and Revolutionary armies buried at the First Presbyterian and Trinity Churches in Pittsburgh. After the death of her husband in 1889, Mary continued expanding the collection of books and manuscripts about western Pennsylvania history. Materials in this series relate to Mary's research and writing, personal correspondence and legal and financial papers that document her vast real estate holdings. Mary compiled and collected historical documents, including Indian treaties; she also maintained records of materials loaned from the family library. Her writings, both epic and non-fiction, represented here, include a brief history of carpets, and her English language adaptation of the German Story of Nibelungen. Two copies of her lengthy manuscript The Exiles of Erin on Ireland and its noble families, are accompanied by an index listing section titles and corresponding page numbers, and a list of secondary sources that Mary used to write the work. A twenty-nine page manuscript written by Mary documents the history of the O'Hara family.
  This series also contains two letters from acquaintances, William Roseburg, an investment banker from Pittsburgh, and William R. Mercer of Doylestown, Pennsylvania. A photographic print produced by Mr. Jarrett shows silhouettes of Mary as a small child with her elderly grandmother, Mary Carson O'Hara. Also present is a list of the many mortgages paid to Mary, and a list of bonds she held from companies such as the Aspinwall Delafield Company, the Pittsburgh Railway Company, the McKeesport Railway Company, the Connersville Railway Company, the Youngstown Railway Company, and the West Penn Railway Company.
  - Treaty between the Governor of Virginia and the United Nations of Tudiaus, 1753 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - School tax receipt, 1839-1851 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - List of maps loaned to H. M. Bradford, July, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - William Roseburg to Mary Carson O'Hara Darlington, July 16, 1904 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - William R. Mercer to Mary Carson O'Hara Darlington, October 10, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Mortgages and Principles, February 24, 1903 - September 26, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Notes on the History of Carpets, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Story of Nibelungen, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Notes on O'Hara Family History, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Silhouettes of Mary Carson O'Hara Darlington and Mary Carson O'Hara, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Exiles of Erin, copy 1, undated (Box 5, Folder 11-23)
  - Exiles of Erin index, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Fort Pitt and Letters from the Frontier, undated (Box 5a, Volume 10)
  - Exiles of Erin, copy 2, undated (Box 6, Folder 1-18)
- O'Hara Darlington Papers, 1874-1916; V.
  O'Hara Darlington (1849-1916), was the oldest child of William M. Darlington and Mary Carson O'Hara Darlington. O'Hara was an accomplished scholar in history, botany, and literature. He attended the Western University of Pennsylvania, and enrolled at Yale University with the class of 1870, where he joined the Delta Kappa Fraternity. Due to ill health, O'Hara left Yale at the end of his first year, but returned in 1871 and obtained his degree with honors. O'Hara shared his family's devotion to expanding their private library. Following his graduation from Yale, he traveled throughout Europe collecting historical artifacts and literature. O'Hara fell ill in Europe, but regained his strength. After his travels, he resided at Guyasuta. O'Hara bought and sold land in the Pittsburgh area, and ventured into the steam boat industry, investing in the transport of freight and passengers along the Allegheny, Monongahela and Ohio rivers. On August 22, 1916, O'Hara died suddenly at Guyasuta from heat prostration at the age of sixty-seven following a serious illness.
  O'Hara shared a passion for photography with his sister, Edith, both of whom belonged to the Pittsburgh Amateur Photographers' Society. O'Hara collected late nineteenth century British and American literature, principally fiction. Amid his collection of approximately 1,000 books are first editions of novels by Dickens and Thackeray, an early edition of Defoe's Robinson Crusoe, as well as a bibliography of George and Robert Cruickshank's sketches.
  O'Hara's papers relate to his book collecting and historical research, including receipts from two book companies and his membership in the Historical Society of Pennsylvania. His personal record-keeping is highlighted by twelve diaries, with entries concerning the weather, and the time when various flowers and trees blossom. O'Hara periodically describes the affect of droughts and heavy snowfall on his land, as well as the height of Pittsburgh's three rivers. He also includes brief notes about business meetings, court cases and property issues that concern him. The diaries also describe travel including trips to Atlantic City, New Jersey; Florida; and Chicago during the 1893 World's Columbian Exhibition.
  Many of the diaries contain notes of interest accrued on investments, rent and mortgage money paid or earned for the year. Additional materials relate to O'Hara's finances, include property tax receipts, notes on a legal case involving property he wished to procure, and documentation of various stocks and bonds he held. The series also contains his diploma from Yale and his obituary and funeral bill. For more information, please refer to Box 25, which contains oversized materials.
  - Document summarizing court proceedings, April 17, 1874 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Letters from the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, October 18, 1890 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Receipts and Letters, November 30, 1891-April 2, 1894 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Taxes, O'Hara Township, 1915 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Taxes, O'Hara Township and Aspinwall Borough, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Obituary, August 25, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Funeral Bill, September 9, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Yale University crest, 1871 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - List of Stocks owned by O'Hara Darlington, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Personal Diaries, 1890-1892 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Personal Diaries, 1893-1895 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Personal Diaries, 1896-1898 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Personal Diaries, 1899, 1906, 1909 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Ground Lease, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Yale Memorabilia Scrapbook, 1868-1871 (Box 5a, Volume 53)
    Contains various event programs, exam questions, and tuition statements.
- Mary Carson Darlington Papers, 1867-1916; VI.
  Mary Carson Darlington (1852-1925), the eldest daughter of William M. Darlington and Mary Carson O'Hara Darlington, attended the Pittsburgh School of Design and was an influential member of the Pittsburgh chapter of the Daughters of American Revolution. Mary Carson Darlington never married and continued to live at her parent's mansion 'Guyasuta' until the later years of her life. When Mary Carson Darlington and her sister, Edith Darlington Ammon, sold the property, they bought a large house in the East End of Pittsburgh. After Edith Darlington Ammon died in 1919, Mary Carson Darlington continued to live alone in their East End home until her death six years later in 1925.
  Within Mary Carson Darlington's papers is tax information on her mother's estate and properties that she had inherited with her sister and older brother upon the death of their parents. Mary Carson Darlington also saved a particular book plate of George Washington given to her by her father, as she too was interested in historical preservation. Also included in this collection are pieces of Artwork created by Mary Carson Darlington, which can be found in series XII.
  - Taxes, 1915 and 1916 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - George Washington Bookplate, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Watercolors and Sketches by Mary Carson Darlington, undated (Box 7, Folder 17-20)
  - Photograph of Mary Carson Darlington and friend, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Edith Dennison Darlington Ammon Papers, 1881-1882, 1908-1919; VII.
  Edith "Darling" Dennison Darlington Ammon (1862-1919) was an important figure among Pittsburgh's social elite during the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. She was a well-traveled amateur photographer who played an active role in organizing and leading political and social events.
  Edith grew up at Guyasuta and later studied at the Pittsburgh Female College, now known as Chatham University. After a formative trip to Europe with her family, she married Samuel Ammon in 1890, whose proposal she had previously rejected or deferred ten years earlier. Edith and Samuel had no children.
  Edith served for several years as the president of the Daughters of the American Revolution (DAR) of Allegheny County, and by 1908 she was leading the third largest DAR chapter in the United States. As president, Edith commanded the battle to preserve the Block House, one of the first structures of Fort Pitt built during the French and Indian War in 1764, from destruction by the Pennsylvania Railroad Company. The DAR also led a campaign against Henry Frick when he planned to relocate the Block House to present day Schenley Park. The Block House remains the oldest building in western Pennsylvania. In addition to her work with the DAR, Edith served alongside H. J. Heinz as co-vice president of the 1908 general committee for Pittsburgh's sesquicentennial events.
  This series contains the many letters Edith wrote to her childhood friend and Pittsburgh Female College classmate, Mittie Hemphill, while Edith traveled with her family in Europe from 1881 to 1882. As a woman in her early twenties, Edith writes from each destination, describing the hotels where she and her family stayed, fellow guests, transit, and her experiences passing through customs. Her letters detail sightseeing, particularly art galleries and churches, and her father's research endeavors at the British Museum. Of particular note are Edith's descriptions of archaeological sites in Italy and Egypt, the Salon de Paris, and her distaste for the famous Whistler paintings on display in London. Edith collected or created souvenirs, photographs and artwork during her travels, including a framed photograph of herself at the Temple of Iris in Pompeii, Italy. Mittie's letters describe events in Pittsburgh, including the health of Edith's dogs at Guyasuta and activities of mutual acquaintances in Pittsburgh, among them Minnie Renshaw, Kate McKnight, and Edith's aunt, Helen Evans. In one letter, Mittie mentions Edith's indignation that Samuel Ammon had not waited the appropriate two month grieving period before having a party; the name of the deceased is not mentioned.
  Materials related to Edith's involvement in the DAR include an article she wrote for the Pittsburgh Bulletin, and a letter from Thomas P. Roberts regarding the renovations to Fort Pitt co-sponsored by the Fort Pitt Society and the DAR. The collection also includes a letter from Sydney Liggett in response to Edith's request for information about the Sharp family, and a letter from Edith's husband, Samuel A. Ammon, to Mrs. Mary Echler regarding the possession of the Whitaker graveyards. Records of Edith's stocks and bonds, and two copies of a bound volume listing the properties she inherited from her mother's estate are also present.
  - Darlington-Hemphill correspondence envelopes, 1881-82 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, London, September 25, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, London, October 9, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, London, October 18-19, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, London, October 23, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, London, October 24, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Paris, November 7, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Paris, November 25, 26, 28, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Aix les Bains, November 30, 1881-December 2, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Edith Dennison Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Turin, December 4, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Milan and Genoa, December 5, 7-8, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Florence, December 10-11, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Florence, December 14-15, 19, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Rome, December 24-25, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Rome, December 29-31, 1881 and January 1, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Naples, January 7-8, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Naples, January 12, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Sorrento, January 17-18, 20, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Ship to Alexandria, January 22-25, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Alexandria, January 26, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Edith Darlington to Mittie Hemphill, Alexandria, January 26, 28-30, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 21)